Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Albums (Album File) circa 1880-circa 1980 (bulk 1860-1920) PR 2
New-York Historical Society
- [Album of architectural drawings by John Trumbull], circa 1790's; 57224 (Volume 466)
  Volume of architectural drawings by painter John Trumbull, which he presented to celebrated architect Alexander Jackson Davis, who studied with Trumbull. The album contains sketches made in London, Paris, Washington, New York, and New Haven. Among the buildings depicted are the "Old Almshouse" and Custom House in New York, the state capital of Indiana, and the U.S. Capital in Washington, D.C.
- [Example of 18th century binding], 57225 (Volume 467)
- [Family Photograph Album that belonged to Edith Haeselbarth Carrillo], ca. 1860-1900; 80660 (Volume 468)
  Album of mostly unidentified family photographs including carte de visites, cabinet cards, and tintypes. Album once belonged to Edith Haeselbart Carrillo, a WWI ambulance driver and wife of actor Leo Carrillo. She was born in Nyack, NY in 1885, and died in Los Angeles CA on July 24, 1953.
- [Webb/Vanderbilt and Elder/Havemeyer family album], ca. 1860-1890; 81722 (Volume 469.1 & 469.2)
  Album of carte de visites, cabinet cards, and prints of the families of William Seward Webb and Lila Osgood Vanderbilt, and Louisine W. Elder and Henry Osbourne Havemeyer. The photographs, along with some biographical information about some of the family members, were placed in a binder by the donor. An empty carte de visite album dated 1861 was included in the donation.
  Donated April 15, 2015 by Ursula M. Kammer-Fox
- N-O-N-S-E-N-S-E [WWI Scrapbook], 1918; 82742 (Volume 470)
  A Few Poems And Other Things Put Together In Spare Moments While Serving With The A.E.F. In France By Arthur Ritter. Scrapbook includes type-written poems, pass for leave in Paris, WWI graphics, photographs, and other ephemera.
  Gift of Valerie Paley, 2015.
  Related Materials
  Arthur Ritter is included in a group photograph of the Third Battalion 34th Engineers at Camp Dix, New Jersey, also donated by Valerie Paley. The photograph is held in the Portrait File, PR 52.
- [Album of cabinet cards and carte de visites], ca. 1860-1870; 82749 (Volume 471)
  Unsolicited donation, Camden NJ Public Library 2015
- The Pepsi-Cola Spectacular, circa 1955; 83105 (Volume 472)
  Album documenting the creation and installation of the Pepsi Cola "spectacular" electric sign in Times Square, featuring a 120 foot waterfall that pumped 50,000 gallons of water a minute. The sign was designed by Doug Leigh and constructed by Artkraft Strauss Sign Corp.
- [Album of photographs documenting a family's trip to Europe in 1912, sailing on the S.S. George Washington], 87893 (Volume 473)
- [Scrapbook about The Gramercy Apartment House at 34 Gramercy Park East], 91557 (Volume 474)
  General Note
  The 2 scrapbooks have been disbound and rehoused.
  gift of Dr. Mico Nelson, 2015
- [Partial scrapbook of Mrs. Roberta Carr], 1940's-1950's; 109429 (Volume 475)
  Scope and Contents Note
  This scrapbook contains items relating to the Spence School for Girls (pamphlets, commencement announcements, invitations, etc.) as well as playbills, ticket stubs, a Coney Island puzzle and a pamphlet titled "The Art of Middle Aisling for the Bridegroom."
- [Album of William and Florence Schuette], 109430 (Volume 476)
  Family album of William and Florence Schuette. William Schuette (died 1923) owned a lumber company and the family resided at 375 Park Avenue. Includes travel photos, portraits of family and friends, photos of dogs, clippings, etc.
- [Photo album of Mrs. James J. Walker on trip to Hamburg, Germany], 1920's; 111748 (Volume 477)
  Wife of Mayor James J. Walker; includes photos of her exercising in ship gymnasium.
- Sarony Photographic Art Album for Steamship Idlewild, 1870s; 195217 (Volume 478)
  Acquisition Note
  Gift of James Olinkiewicz, 2016
  This album contains photographic portraits and reproductions of advertisements for various businesses. It was created by Sarony Studio, founded by the lithographer Napoleon Sarony (1821-1896), continued by his son Otto Sarony (1859-1903). Sarony Studio dominated the theatrical portraiture market during the latter half of the 19th century.
- [Partial album of Edna Rhoode Munger], ca. 1930s-1940s; 204664 (Volume 479)
  2 pages from an album, containing vacation photographs from Niagara Falls; Erie, PA; Lake Cuba, NY; and Madison, CT.
- [Brooklyn Edison Club scrapbook], ca. 1920s; 204674 (Volume 480)
  This scrapbook contains photographs of and clippings about athletes and athletic events connected with the Brooklyn Edison Club. Individuals featured include fencer Agnes Conlon, and swimmer Walter Ribiero. The album also includes two photos of the Brooklyn Edison baseball team.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
  Gift of Michael Moran, 2015
- [Partial album of John V. Van Siclen], ca. 1900; 204708 (Volume 481)
  Four photographs of old buildings in Brooklyn and Queens, with captions. Includes images of Alley Store in Alley Park, Queens; the Ammerman house on Avenue M and Nostrand Avenue, Brooklyn (2 copies); and Hendrick Lott house on Jamaica Avenue, Queens.
  Gift of the Holland Society of New York, 2017
- [McGarty family scrapbook], ca. 1800s-1900s; 221977 (Volume 482)
  26 folders of photographs (most identified), genealogical documents, and ephemera from the McGarty, Norris, Jorgensen, Marshall, Gerolstein, and Concannon families of Brooklyn and elsewhere. Includes an autograph album with entries dated 1904, and some explanatory information supplied by the donor.
  Gift of Patricia McGarty Laidlaw, September 2017 (PPAC.2017.65).
- [Photo album of New York Harbor and Europe after World War I], ca. 1918-1921; 222147 (Volume 483)
  Includes post-World War I snapshots of New York Harbor and vicinity, and landmarks in European cities such as Paris, Rheims, Versailles, Brussels, and Wiesbaden.
  Gift of Nancy Slicker, October 2017 (PPAC.2017.71).
- [Photo album of the Maurice Brill residence, 163 East 63rd Street, Manhattan], ca. 1919 (Volume 484)
  Album of 11 photographs by Schuyler Cartaret Lee of the exterior and interior of the Maurice Brill residence, no. 163 East 63rd Street, Manhattan. In 1919 architect Frederick Sterner (1862–1931) combined and remodeled two adjoining brownstones (163 and 165 East 63rd Street) to create the Brill residence. John Hay "Jock" Whitney (1904–1982), a later owner of the house, hired architect Ellery Husted (ca. 1901–1967) to remodel the façade in the neo-Federal style it wears today.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Kathryn Brill, granddaughter of Maurice Brill, January 2018 (PPAC.2018.001).
- [World War II scrapbook of Harold Alden Dike], 1942-1945 (Volume 485)
  Scrapbook apparently compiled by the mother of U.S. Army PFC Harold Alden Dike (1919–2011), of Clarkstown, Rockland County, New York. Dike was inducted into the service in 1942 (see the Selective Service letter tipped in near the start of the volume). The scrapbook bears a pre-printed title—"PHOTOGRAPHS"—and is labeled (in ink) "Vol. I," but aside from 19 photographs (possibly sent home from training camp), the scrapbook consists largely of ephemera and newspaper clippings related to World War II. [Dike was later founding master of the Windy Hollow Hunt, a traditional fox hunt held in the Hudson River Valley.]
  Gift of Susan McInerey, May 2018 (PPAC.2018.025).
  Credit line: "Susan and Kathleen McInerney."
- [New York City photographs], circa 1920s (Volume 486)
  Seven small photographs collected by the donor's father, some labeled: Flatiron Building viewed from inside Madison Square; downtown street view; South Ferry & Central Park horse car; view of The Tribune and other buildings from top of the "World"; Washington's tomb; Staten Island ferry and skyline behind; Statue of Liberty with four airplanes in formation flying above. (Loose, in an envelope)
  Gift of Carol Byron, 2018.
- [Walter Propper photographs], circa 1938-1961 (Volume 487)
  Fourteen loose photograph album leaves holding 100 gelatin silver prints (mostly black-and-white) and 2 newspaper clippings. According to the donor, the photographs were taken by her husband's grandfather, Walter Propper (1893–1970), a New York City native and president of Propper Roofing Company, which explains the number of shots of rooftops and repair work. Among the views are some of named family members and coworkers. Locations include Connecticut, Long Island, and Manhattan, as well as several Bronx sites: Cardinal Hayes High School (650 Grand Concourse); Fire Engine Company 46 (451-453 East 176th Street); St. Barnabas Hospital; Cross Bronx Expressway during construction; 940 Grand Concourse; Park Avenue looking north from 176th Street; 626 Prospect Avenue; 643 Prospect Avenue; 178th Street and Ryer Avenue; 317 East 178th Street (looking north from the roof of); and the Cross Bronx Expressway during construction. Also present is a color snapshot of "Olaf the Walrus," a resident of the New York Aquarium, with his accompanying obituary from the New York Times of December 15, 1966: "Olaf, the Walrus, Is Dead at 10; Long a Favorite at Aquarium."
  Gift of Marcy Propper, March 2018 (accession no. PPAC-2018-013).